Kiwamu Okabe - Research and Development Engineer

Phone: +81-90-3524-7064 Email: kiwamu@debian.or.jp

Homepage: http://masterq.metasepi-design.com/

Interests

I launched my career on developing embedded devices at Ricoh Company, Ltd, and also learned application design using functional language such like Haskell. I found Metasepi project¹ what is trying to apply strong type to embedded programming. For my first challenging, I developed an embedded Haskell compiler named Ajhc², and published some research papers³.

Today, I choose ATS language⁴ as embedded functional language, and found "Japan ATS User Group⁵" what holds Japanese translations about the language. And I'm implementing⁶ these technology on tiny MCU such like ARM Cortex-M series and 8bit AVR for practical use.

Metasepi is very experimental and ambitious project, however I believe that it also introduces an by-product "the technology to design real software with predictable manpower and safety" regardless of embedded domain.

Work Experience

November 2016 - Present: Expert Engineer (permanent employee) at SELTECH CORPORATION

- Maintain a Hypervisor for embedded market
- Design and develop own secure OS for ARM platform

August 2014 - Present: Part-time Researcher at RIKEN Advanced Institute for Computational Science

- Research embedded functional programming running on ARM Cortex-M and AVR
- Verification for RTOS application such like ChibiOS/RT⁷ running on ARM Cortex-M

July 2013 - Present: Self-employed Software Engineer at METASEPI DESIGN

- Research and develop Ajhc Haskell Compiler
- Host meetups⁸ for hands-on to verify embedded application on ARM Cortex-M using STM32⁹ board and ST-LINK¹⁰ debugger

¹ http://www.metasepi.org/

²http://ajhc.metasepi.org/

³http://www.metasepi.org/papers.html

⁴http://www.ats-lang.org/

⁵http://jats-ug.metasepi.org/

⁶http://fpiot.metasepi.org/

⁷http://www.chibios.org/

⁸https://metasepi.connpass.com/

⁹http://www.st.com/en/microcontrollers/stm32-32-bit-arm-cortex-mcus.html

¹⁰ http://www.st.com/en/development-tools/st-link.html

- ATS language evangelist
- Verification evangelist using VeriFast¹¹, which is a verifier C language programs annotated with preconditions and postconditions
- Translated VeriFast Tutorial into Japanese 12
- Support to develop any embedded software
- Manage Metasepi Project and develop the core technology

February 2016 - November 2016: Software Enginner (contract employee) at Life Robotics Inc.

- Design GUI application running on Linux OS, using C++ and Qt¹³
- Design network protocol for Robotics application
- Reason for Quitting: to challenge verification of secure application using C language and VeriFast

March 2015 - February 2016: System Enginner (contract employee) at Centillion Japan Co., Ltd.

- Technical support for stock chart application using JavaScript
- Maintain MySQL database servers
- Launch new IoT business for farming
- Design a platform ¹⁴ to accelerate R programs
- Reason for Quitting: to change my job into embedded one, again

September 2014 - December 2014: Software engineer (trustee agreement) at Axsh co., LTD.

- Develop an OpenFlow application named "OpenVNet" 15
- Design automation scripts for AWS using Ruby and GNU make
- Reason for Quitting: to have better salary

March 2012 - July 2013: Software Engineer (permanent employee) at MIRACLE LINUX CORPORATION

- Maintain own Digital Signage platform running on Intel architecture using Linux OS, C++, OpenGL, GTK+¹⁶ and GStreamer¹⁷
- Verify and tune up performance of Digital Signage on new Intel platform and Intel video driver
- Verify PowerPC Linux kernel and debug/fix a race condition in the SMP kernel

¹¹https://github.com/verifast/verifast

¹²https://github.com/jverifast-ug/translate/blob/master/Manual/Tutorial/Tutorial.md

¹³https://www.qt.io/

¹⁴https://github.com/centillion-tech/kick-r

¹⁵https://github.com/axsh/openvnet

¹⁶https://www.gtk.org/

¹⁷https://gstreamer.freedesktop.org/

- Debug and fix bug of crash¹⁸ command's PowerPC virtual memory paging
- Design new Windows installer using NSIS¹⁹
- Introduce and maintain new Git server for internal use
- Reason for Quitting: to focus researching and developing Ajhc Haskell compiler on full-time work

April 2001 - February 2012: Software Development Engineer (permanent employee) at Ricoh Company, Ltd.

- Develop BIOS and bootloader for multifunction printer on Intel architecture
- Design secure boot for multifunction printer on Intel architecture
- Develop new BIOS for multifunction printer
- Tune multifunction printer boot time as 10 seconds
- Develop POSIX thread library
- Develop and technical support NetBSD OS
- Port OS to new Intel hardware
- Reason for Quitting: to join more small and quick team

Education

 March 2001: Master of Engineering from Department of Electrical and Electronic Engineering, Tokyo Metropolitan University.

The thesis: "Multimode Quartz Crystal Microbalance" ²⁰

Publications and Reports

- Kiwamu Okabe and Hongwei Xi. "Arduino programing of ML-style in ATS" 21. ML workshop, 2015.
- Kiwamu Okabe and Takayuki Muranushi. "Systems Demonstration: Writing NetBSD Sound Drivers in Haskell" 22. Haskell Symposium, 2014.
- Kiwamu Okabe. "ATS 言語を使って不変条件を API に強制する".²³ 夏のプログラミング・シンポジウム 2014, 2014.
- Kiwamu Okabe, Hiroki MIZUNO and Hidekazu SEGAWA. "強い型による OS の開発手法の提案" ²⁴. 第 55 回プログラミング・シンポジウム, 2014.

¹⁸http://people.redhat.com/~anderson/

¹⁹http://nsis.sourceforge.net/

²⁰http://ci.nii.ac.jp/naid/110004076869

 $^{^{21} \}texttt{http://www.metasepi.org/doc/metasepi-icfp2015-arduino-ats.pdf}$

²²http://metasepi.org/doc/metasepi-icfp2014-demo.pdf

²³http://www.metasepi.org/doc/20141101_prosym_summer2014.pdf

²⁴http://metasepi.org/doc/20140110_prosym55.pdf

Activities

Open-source projects

Metasepi Project²⁵

- Challenge to create an open-source Unix-like operating system designed with strong type such as ML or Haskell.
- Rewriting NetBSD kernel using Ajhc Haskell compiler. https://github.com/metasepi/netbsd-arafura-s1

Ajhc Haskell compiler²⁶

- Extend and add embedded features to Jhc Haskell Compiler http://repetae.net/computer/jhc/.
- Ajhc has thread-safe and reentrant runtime. Also has Erlang style GC. It means Ajhc's Haskell context has own GC heap. GC can run on tiny CPU such as Cortex-M3 with 32kB RAM.

Japan ATS User Group²⁷

• An user group for ATS language promotion of utilization. Translating ATS documents into Japanese.

Debian Maintainer²⁸

• Maintained uim package at Debian squeeze, and packages using Haskell at sid.

Carettah²⁹

• A presentation tool written with Haskell. All of my slides³⁰ are created by the tool.

Computer Skills

- Languages: C, C++, Haskell, ATS, Intel/ARM assembler, Ruby, JavaScript, Python
- Platforms: Linux, NetBSD, FreeRTOS, ChibiOS/RT, Android NDK, Cygwin, MinGW, Bare metal

Reference available upon request

- Hiroyasu Fukuyama CTO SELTECH CORPORATION
- \bullet Woo-Keun Yoon CEO Life Robotics Inc.
- Kentaro Kuroiwa Research Chief Centillion Japan Co., Ltd.
- Yasuhiro Yamazaki CEO Axsh Co., Ltd.
- Takayuki Muranushi RIKEN Advanced Institute for Computational Science
- Takashi KODAMA CEO MIRACLE LINUX CORPORATION

 $^{^{25} {}m http://metasepi.org/}$

²⁶http://ajhc.metasepi.org/

²⁷http://jats-ug.metasepi.org/

 $^{^{28} \}verb|http://qa.debian.org/developer.php?login=kiwamu@debian.or.jp|$

²⁹https://github.com/master-q/carettah

³⁰http://www.slideshare.net/master_q/

- $\bullet\,$ Shigeya SENDA Ricoh Company, Ltd.
- Hitoshi Sekimoto Professor Tokyo Metropolitan University, Department of Electrical and Electronic Engineering

Last updated: August 17, 2017